Plastics Product Literature Collection
Plastics Product Literature Collection
1890-2012
National Plastics Center & Museum.
9.5 linear ft.
Collection consists of product literature, catalogs, objects and technical bulletins on plastic products and plastic applications by numerous plastic and chemical companies. Most emanate from American companies but the collection includes some from Japanese companies, as well as a few from France, Germany, Australia and the United Kingdom.
2663589
Biographical History
Founded in 1982, the National Plastics Center (NPC) was a non-profit institution dedicated to preserving the past, addressing the present and promoting the future of plastics through public education and awareness. The Center, which closed in 2008, had an extensive museum collection of plastic parts, machinery and memorabilia and the archives and library contain numerous books and collections on many subjects, companies and people prominent in the industry. In 2011, much of the NPCM collection was donated to Syracuse University.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Plastics Product Literature Collection consists of product literature, catalogs, objects and technical bulletins on plastic products and plastic applications by numerous plastic and chemical companies. Most emanate from American companies but the collection includes some from Japanese companies, as well as a few from France, Germany, Australia and the United Kingdom.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by name of company and chronological within each company.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see the
Irwin Casper Collection of Brush Product Literature
and the
Walter R. Kosy Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Industrial Design; Plastics; Manufacturing processes.; Plastics -- Marketing.; Plastics industry and trade -- Australia.; Plastics industry and trade -- Germany.; Plastics industry and trade -- Japan.; Plastics industry and trade -- United Kingdom.; Plastics industry and trade -- United States.; Trade literature.; Brochures.; Bulletins.; Catalogs (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Technical manuals.; Technical reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority of collection, transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008.
Rogers Corporation binder on molding materials (1973) and United States Gasket Company book (1952-1953), gift of George Marshall Naul, 2011.
Industrial Plastics Products (IPP) material, gift of Veronika Thorne, 2012.
Plastics Packaging Corp. material, gift of Susan Weiss, 2012.
General Electric publicity material gift of James Albright, 2014.
Spirex material, gift of Timothy Womer, 2018.
Pro Corporation material, gift of Glenn Beall, 2018.
Celanese Celluloid Corporation book (1942), gift of James L. Throne, 2019.
Inventory
- Company literature
  - Allied Chemical, 1964-1980; technical service report featuring data on the refrigerant, Genetron, and a booklet on the injection molding of rigid polyvinyl chloride (Box 1)
  - American Cyanamid Company, 1957; technical literature on CYMAC 400 polymethylstyrene molding compounds (Box 1)
  - American Cystoscope Makers, Inc., undated; clipping from "Plastics World" (Box 1)
  - American Hoechst Corporation, undated; brochure This is American Hoechst (Box 1)
  - Amoco, undated; technical bulletin on evaluating Isopolyester resins (Box 1)
  - Anker-Steinbaukasten, circa 1900s; 2 folders; various booklets of designs for Richter's building blocks (Box 1)
  - Aquitaine, [1970]; technical literature on Organico, Rilsan, Aquitane 72, and Lacqran (Box 1)
  - Argus Chemical Corporation, 1969; 1975; technical booklets on mark stabilizers, pvc pipe, and conduit (Box 1)
  - Armstrong Products Company, 1954; technical literature on epoxy resin adhesives (Box 1)
  - Arthur Blank and Company, purchaser catalog containing plastic products for both personal and office use (Box 1)
  - Ashdee, vinyl stickers "put it back where you found it!," advertisement for UV Cure Reactor machine (Box 1)
  - Atlas Electric Devices Company, 1941; 1971,; 1982,; 1985; technical literature and instructions for the Fade-Ometer (Box 1)
  - Auto-Blow Corp (subsidiary of National Cleveland Corp), 1960; technical literature regarding automatic high production blow-molding machines (Box 1)
  - BASF World Sales, 1973; operation fundamentals book (Box 1)
  - Breton Plastics Catalog Fabrication Manual, undated (Box 1)
  - Boonton Molding Company, 1955; 1958,; [1964],; 1973; "a ready reference guide for plastics" book and technical literature regarding plastic materials molding; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Borden Chemical, undated; technical booklet on pvc resins and compounds (Box 2)
  - Borg Warner (Marbon)
    - Technical data, 1957; 1965; Cycoloy, Cyolac ABS, Cycolac high impact thermoplastic resin and various other plastic materials (Box 2)
    - Technical data, 1957; 1964-1969,; 1973-1976,; undated; Cycoloy, Cyolac ABS, Cycolac high impact thermoplastic resin and various other plastic materials; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Branson Instruments, 1973; a guide to ultrasonic plastics assembly (Box 4)
  - Bush Keepsake, undated; photostat pages pf catalog, mostly of wedding cake decorations (Box 4)
  - California Electrotype and Stereotype Company, undated; booklet for ordering electrotype stock cuts (Box 4)
  - Captive Plastics, inc., 1993; Quarterly newsletter The Captivator, vol 3, no. 3 (Box 4)
  - Celanese Plastics Company / Celanese Celluloid Corporation, 1942; 1945,; 1967,; 1973-1974,; 1983-1985; book on "fabricating methods for Lumarith, Celluloid and similar thermoplastic materials," technical literature on Celcon acetal copolymer, celanese nylon and celanex thermoplastic polyester; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Cerro de Paseo Copper Corporation, 1939; "The Cerromatrix Manual, Methods of Using Cerromatrix a Low Temperature Melting Expanding Alloy" (Box 4)
  - Cincinnati Milacron Chemicals, 1963-1973; 1976; technical literature regarding the stabilization of polyvinyl chloride and various other plastic materials (Box 4)
  - Coca-Cola Company, 1993; catalog (Box 4)
  - Commercial Plastics & Supply Corp., 1964; catalog for sheets, rods and tubes (Box 4)
  - Continental-Diamond Fibre, a booklet of technical information regarding Celoron (Box 4)
  - Conwed Corp., 1971; product brochure for Conwed plastic netting products with 1 page insert about rigid polypropylene tubes (Box 4)
  - Danish Plastics, 1959; 1962-1963,; undated; drawings and technical booklets related to the Blow-O-Matic (Box 5)
  - Dartco (Dart & Craft), 1985; technical information regarding injection molding XYDAR (Box 5)
  - DeBell and Richardson, Inc., undated; booklet on the innovation in polymers (Box 5)
  - Detroit Mold Engineering, 1948; 1952-1953; 1957,; 1963,; 1975; dealer ordering books for standard mold bases, parts and supplies; technical data regarding mold bases, injection molding machines, compression molding machines and die casting machines; DME News, Vol 10: 1, 3 (1952) and Vol 11:1 (1953); 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Dow Chemical
    - Technical literature, 1943; 1951-1957; Styron, Polystyrene, Styrex, Ethocel, Saran, Polyethylene and PVC, as well as information regarding the design and properties of plastics; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Technical literature, 1946; 1951-1967; Styron, Polystyrene, Styrex, Ethocel, Saran, Polyethylene and PVC, as well as information regarding the design and properties of plastics; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Dri-Print Foils, Inc., a booklet highlighting the product line (Box 6)
  - DSM Resins UK Ltd., 1991; a folder containing commercial literature regarding Auto Press and the innovations in injection molding (Box 6)
  - Du Pont
    - Promotional material
      - Annual Report, Du Pont: Celebrating the Past, Shaping the Future. Fiftieth Anniversary of Nylon and Teflon, 1987 (Box 6)
      - Better Living: The DuPont Employee Magazine, 1950 (Box 6)
      - Boudoir Accessories catalogs, 1920-1930; Lucite, Pyralin, and Arlton (Box 6)
      - Du Pont News, Vol 6 no. 12, Dec 1977 (Box 6)
      - This is Du Pont, 1949; 52-page promotional magazine about company (Box 6)
    - Technical literature
      - [General], 1956-1961; design, engineering and technical data regarding Alathon, Delrin, Teflon, Zytel Nylon Resin, and Lucite (Box 6)
      - [General], 1956-1962; 1968-1969,; 1972-1978; design, engineering and technical data regarding Alathon, Delrin, Teflon, Zytel Nylon Resin, Lucite, Corian, Hytrel, Neoprene, Teflon and Delrin,; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Durez Plastics Division (Hooker Chemical Corp), 1930; 1951-1960,; 1964,; 1967-1973; 1983; booklets with data regarding molding compounds and phenolics, technical data regarding properties of products and molding techniques, 13 issues of the Durex Molder bulletin; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Eastman Chemical Products (Tenite), 1957; 1967,; undated; book detailing the invention of color film and technical information regarding Tenite (Box 8)
  - Edmark Enterprise, Inc., 1989; catalog of fashion accessories (Box 8)
  - Enjay Chemical Company, technical books regarding Escon Polypropylene (Box 8)
  - Exact Weight Scale Company, 1956; 1965,; undated; instructions for operating the Exact Weight Plastics Weigh Feeder (Box 8)
  - Farrel-Birmingham Company, Inc., 1944; bulletin highlighting Banbury mixers (Box 8)
  - Fellows Gear Shaper Company, 1955; 1960,; undated; instructions for operating the injection molding machine with drawings (Box 8)
  - Fiberite, 1985; materials selection handbook (Box 8)
  - Fibroc, June 5, 1930; pamphlet announcing merger with Continental-Diamond Fibre Co. and their new name, Fibroc Insulation Company (Box 8)
  - Foster Grant, technical bulletin highlighting nylon injection molding problems (Box 8)
  - Fraser and Glass, LTD, undated; drawing of unknown object (Box 8)
  - Furukawa Group, information book highlighting their factories, products and history (Box 8)
  - General Electric
    - Genal Product Line binder, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Lexan (Box 9)
    - Noryl (Box 9)
    - Phenolic Molding Compound, 1946; 1948,; undated (Box 9)
    - Phenolic Molding Compound, 1966-1974; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Textolite, circa 1947 (Box 9)
    - Valox, 1983 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous product information (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous publicity material, 1965 (Box 9)
      Gift of James Albright, 2014.
  - The General Tire and Rubber Company, Bolta Products Division, undated; Boltaron fashion tones samples (Box 9)
  - BF Goodrich (Koroseal), handbook and literature containing technical information related to Koroseal, and a sample of fourteen wires in various colors (Box 10)
  - Hanna Engineering Works, technical book for Hydraulic Cylinders (Box 10)
  - Hercules Powder Company, 1944; technical book for Ethyl Cellulose (Box 10)
  - Hitachi Chemical Products, technical book for their products and materials (Box 10)
  - Hobalite, 1944; technical book for hobbed mold dies (Box 10)
  - Hoechst, 1965; 1987; technical binder regarding organic pigments for PVC with samples (Box 10)
  - Hottwatt Electric Heaters, 1981; distributor catalog of discounts and prices for heaters (Box 10)
  - ICI (Imperial Chemical Industries), 1966; 1969; technical literature on Cereclor; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Idemitsu Petrochemical Co., LTD, [1972]; booklet of company history and statistics (Box 11)
  - IMS Co. (Injection Molders Supply), 1951; 1968-1969,; 1986-1987; catalog of supplies for the injection molder, injection machine nozzle handbook, accessory plant equipment for injection molders book, and an auxiliary machinary packet for plastic processors; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Incoe Corporation, undated; technical booklet regarding the hot tip bushings manifold system (Box 11)
  - Industrial Plastics Products, Inc., undated; folder with company information and illustrations of products (Box 11)
  - International Paper, 1997-1999; nine product information promotional booklets and fact sheets about laminates from Nevamar Decorative Products Division (Box 11)
  - Interstab Chemicals, Inc., 1974; technical manual on stabilizers, chelators, blowing agent catalysts, organotin stabilizers, and lubricants (Box 11)
  - Japan Gas Chemical Co., book containing company history (Box 11)
  - Japan Synthetic Rubber Co., [1970]; book containing company and product history (Box 11)
  - Jeuffroy & Fils, [1890]; album with 39 pages illustrating machinery used for the manufacture of combs from horn, rubber nad celluloid (Box 11)
  - Kanebo, pamphlet containing their products and materials used (Box 11)
  - Kelvinator (Adelaide Australia), [1965]; book discussing molding, processes and machinary (Box 11)
  - Kent Plastics, book highlighting their products and factory locations (Box 11)
  - Kleinewefers, 1962; book on company history and progress (Box 11)
  - Koehring, 1973; 2 booklets on Prodex extrusion systems (Box 11)
  - Koppers Co., technical bulletins on troubleshooting injection molding problems, adhesive for polystyrene and Dylite (Box 11)
  - Krauss Maffei, 1988; 1991; catalogs for machinary and technical journals (Box 12)
  - Kureha Chemical, 1970; book containing company history and product information (Box 12)
  - Kyowa Gas Chemical, 1970; typed booklet containing company history, a diagram of manufacturing process and two photographs of factories (Box 12)
  - Lego, 2009; holiday consumer catalog of lego products (Box 12)
  - Lehigh Valley Plastics, ordering catalog for their plastic sheets, rods and tubes (Box 12)
  - Leominster Tool Co., Inc., 1984 (Box 12)
  - Lily-Tulip Cup Corporation, undated; company history and product booklet (Box 12)
  - LNP, 1980; 1985,; undated; a guide to statically conductive and EMI attenuating composites, technical bulletins on thermoplastics and fluoropolymer composites (Box 12)
  - Lyon Inc., magazine ad for Whitewalls trim ring for automobile tires (Box 12)
  - Magnus Harmonica Corporation, 1946-1948; 1989; book entitled, "Precision Builds an Industry, The Story of the Magnus Harmonica Corporation," contianed within are reprints of old newspaper clippings and ads (Box 12)
  - Mattel, Inc., undated; book of mold standards with drawings (Box 12)
  - McNeil Akron, undated; booklet on machinary and products (Box 12)
  - Mitsubishi Petrochemical Company Limited, 1967; book containing company history, statistics and product information (Box 12)
  - Modern Plastics, 1995; retail order form, product information catalog for Defender Interior Insulating Windows,product list and a green plastic sample (Box 12)
  - Monsanto
    - Product material, 1963-1964; 1969; product magazines featuring greenhouses and furniture, Lustran San price schedule (Box 12)
    - Technical material, 1961; 1964,; 1969,; 1976,; undated; two technical books regarding plasticizers and resin modifiers, and technical information on Lustrex L and LX Styrenes; 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Morgan Industries, book entitled, "Cutting Costs in Short-Run Plastics Injection Molding" featuring injection molding process, tool design and building, part design and material selection, epoxy tooling and material handling (Box 14)
  - The M.S. Plastics Co., undated; facilities report (Box 14)
  - Nalle Plastics, Inc., [1963]; Naltex netting information and samples (Box 14)
  - Newbury Industries, Inc., 1969; information on plastic injection molding machines, "mini-jector" (Box 14)
  - Nichimen Co., LTD, 1968; book from the 12th National Plastics Exposition with company and plastic material history (Box 14)
  - NL Industries, [1972]; technical information regarding Titanox titanium pigments (Box 14)
  - Novacor Chemicals, Inc. (a subsidiary of Nova Corporation of Alberta), 1991; "Nova World" employee publication (Box 14)
  - Nypro, 1998; 2000-2002,; 2005; The Nypro Institute booklets, "Plastics Innovation for Fifty Years" booklets, and an annual report from the company (Box 14)
  - Olsen Testing Machine Company, 1941; information booklet for their impact testing machine with "change-o-matic" head (Box 14)
  - Owens-Corning Fiberglas Corporation
    - Promotional material, undated; Textile Products Division folder "More product problems solved with reinforced molding compounds" (Box 14)
    - Technical material, 1943; fiberglas development programs and their indicated uses (Box 14)
  - PARR Moulding Compounds Corp., [1960]; information on the tests they conduct on their materials and products (Box 14)
  - Pasadena Hydraulics, Inc.., undated; 8-page booklet "PHI Injection Molding Machines" with diazo blueline print insert illustration by E. J. Delgado of a medium size injection molding machine (Box 14)
  - Phillips Chemical Company, 1959; [1964] (Box 14)
  - Pioneer Mold Co, 1947; Tool & Die journal article, "An Electronic Aid in Die Making" (Box 14)
  - Pixley Richards, Inc., 1980-1988; three promotional booklets (Box 15)
  - Plaskon Co., 1939; handbook containing the properties of molded Plaskon and the technique of molding Plaskon (Box 15)
  - Plasticor, undated; clipping of advertisement in "Plastics World" (Box 15)
  - Plasticraft, Inc., craft instructional book for "Dolie-Craft" doll outfits (Box 15)
  - Plastics Packaging Corp., 2012; promotional folder with insert describing and illustrating product lines (Box 15)
  - Plastics Unlimited, customer pamphlet with a list of their products, properties, and distributors (Box 15)
  - Plastics Engineering Co. (Plenco), 1970; 1976; 1997-1998; price schedules for various plastic materials, and technical information for phenolic molding compounds (Box 15)
  - Polyplastex United, Inc., 1960-1961; information on Royaltex (Box 15)
  - Plume & Atwood Mfg, product catalog for washers and rivets (Box 15)
  - Polaroid, 1940; 1989; book entitled, "Polaroid Access, Fifty Years" by Richard Saul Wurman, and a product catalog (Box 15)
  - Pro Corporation, circa 1989; 1995; newsletter, corporate brochure (Box 15)
  - Racine Hydraulics & Machinery, 1944-1949; 1956,; undated; technical catalogs and data for products, and diagrams for 4-way valves, check valves and pressure gauges (Box 15)
  - Raschig, 1985; technical product booklet for resins and molding compounds (Box 15)
  - Raybestos–Manhattan, Inc., 1956; technical data for R/M Pyrotex Molding Compounds, and a bulletin of engineering data for reinforced plastics (Box 15)
  - Reed Prentice, 1966; technical booklet on how to evaluate screw injection machine plasticating performance (Box 15)
  - Resinous Products & Chemical Company, 1944; price schedule for resin adhesives, Tego resin film, Amberlite and Uformite (Box 15)
  - Rexall Chemical Co.
    - Technical information, 1961; 1966,; 1972,; 1979,; undated; reciprocating screw machine, Polypropylene, Polyethylene and El Rex brand products, information on correcting molding faults (Box 15)
    - Technical information, [1975]; undated; Polypropylene, Polyethylene, Polystyrene, powders and resins; measurement tools,; 7 folders (Box 16)
  - Rogers Corporation, 1973; technical information for plastics molding materials (Box 17)
  - Rohm & Hass Company, 1954; 1965-1968,; 1974; samples of plexiglas, technical information on molding powder product design, solving light control problems with plexiglas, and Monoplex and Paraplex plasticizers; 3 folders (Box 17)
  - B. Shackman & Co., 1923; wholesale catalog number 51 favors and novelties for easter etc., 48 pp (Box 17)
  - Seaward International, Inc., 1994; technical manuals Seapile recycled plastic information, and various other boat/marine products (Box 17)
  - Sekisui Plastics, 1969; book containing company and product history (Box 17)
  - Showa Denko KK (SDK), 1968; book of technical information for light metals, ferroalloys, electrodes, abrasive grains, synthetic resins, organic and inorganic chemicals, and fertilizers (Box 17)
  - Silvatrim Mouldings, 1962; product information and samples for Silvatrim (Box 17)
  - Singer Manufacturing Company, 1950; product literature and instructions for Singer electronic seamer for bonding thermoplastic materials (Box 17)
  - SMS Plastics Technology, 2002; a Modern Plastics custom publication featuring an article on Battenfeld injection molding machines and technology (Box 18)
  - Society of the Plastics Industry (SPI), 1978; distributor book entitled, "Standards and Practices of Plastics Molders and Plastics Molded Parts Buyers Guide" (Box 18)
  - Solar Chemical Corporation, 1960; plastic weight comparator and a plastic weight converter (Box 18)
  - South Bend Lathe Works, 1938-1939; bulletin on how to cut screw threads in the lathe and an apprentice training book for a machine shop course (Box 18)
  - Spin-Cast Plastics, Inc., undated; Spin-Cast rotational moulding advertisement (Box 18)
  - Spirex Corporation, 1985; 1992,; circa 2007; several editions of corporate booklet "for reference and education"; titles differ; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Springborn Laboratories, 1992; book of technical information regarding trends in end-use markets for plastics, such as aviation/space and apparel/footwear (Box 18)
  - Standard Tool Company, undated; technical booklet for molds, beryllium copper, and steel castings (Box 18)
  - Starplast Industries, undated; product catalog (Box 18)
  - Sterling Extruder Corporation, undated; book of technical information regarding manufacturing, research and development, engineering, and several machines, such as the Sterling Series (Box 18)
  - Sumitomo Chemical Co., LTD, undated; Japanese technical book (Box 18)
  - Sun Chemical Corporation, 1963; 35th annual report (Box 18)
  - Taber Instrument Corporation, undated; book discussing the quality of their products and the various testing each goes through, specifically the Taber Abraser Test (Box 18)
  - Tech-Art Plastic Company, undated; molders' manual (Box 18)
  - Tennessee Eastman Corporation (subsidiary of Eastman Kodak Company), 1940; 1944; technical information for Tenite (Box 18)
  - Tokuyama Soda Co., LTD, 1970; book of company history and technical information for their materials (Box 18)
  - Tucker, undated; consumer catalogs of their products (Box 18)
  - UBE Laboratories, 1966; 1968,; 1970; two books discussing their industrial history and a technical book on polyethylene (Box 19)
  - Union Carbide & Bakelite, 1938; 1955-1957,; 1974; purchaser's guide on plastics for molding and extrusion, technical information on molding materials and Bakelite, brochure announcing Bakelite Cellulose Acetate, technical data on vinyl rigid sheets and Parylene conformal coatings; 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Uniroyal, undated; Royalite thermoplastic materials technical information (Box 19)
  - United States Gasket Corporation, 1953-1954; "Final Report, Feb. 15, 1953 to June 15, 1954, Investigation of Filled Teflon, Fluorocarbon Products, Inc., Div. of United States Gasket Company, Camden, NJ, Navy Department Bureau of Ships Electronics Division" (Box 19)
  - United States Plastic Corporation, 2001; consumer ordering catalog of products, such as Glutton containers and Smokers Cease-Fire cigarette disposal containers (Box 19)
  - Vetrotex CertainTeed (Glassline), 1992; product information catalog featuring FRP panels (Box 19)
  - Valentine Sugars, Inc., 1989; technical data book (Box 19)
  - Whitehead & Hoag, circa 1900; envelope printed with logo, motto, etc. (Box 19)